soft engineering radio episode 123
Microsoft Oslo with done box and dark
birdie this is software engineering
radio the podcast for professional
developers on the web at s II - radio
dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
welcome listeners to another episode of
software engineering radio this one is
going to be about Oslo obviously not
about the city but rather about the
Microsoft technology called Oslo and
with us on the call on this episode or
two Microsoft is one is don box and the
other one is stark pretty so I don't
know who wants to start maybe each of
you introduce yourself quickly to our
audience great hi I'm Don box I work at
Microsoft I've been here since 2002 I've
been working on Oslo and kind of the
seed technologies that feed into it for
since I would say like 2005 maybe even a
little bit earlier and we've been really
trying to crack this nut of how to
efficiently capture what a developer is
thinking into a form that we can process
and you know I think I can see me into
the light at the end of the tunnel so
I'm I feel like run the good part of the
project now where it's getting close to
the end
doc I'm Doug Purdy I am our Microsoft as
well I help run part of the Oslo team
primarily focused on languages I've been
with Microsoft since 1998 on and off
there's a good story in there baby
maybe one day over drinks so and I've
been you know prior to actually working
on Oslo did a lot of work in the web
services space as well as distributed
computing and now we're very focused on
making it much simpler for folks to
write applications and any of their
applications and a pretty
straightforward way I view this Oslo
effort is really taking programming -
it's sort of next level and enabling a
lots more people to program down and
write down their intent um with our
platform okay so um as you as you might
know it as our listeners certainly know
I'm also very much into this dsl stuff
so this is a topic that I am personally
bit personally very interested in and
I'm quite happy to have you guys on the
show today I'm sure you say that all
your guests well you have to listen to
all 120 episodes to find this out I
guess
so you already mentioned a couple of
high-level thoughts about Oslo so why
don't you one of you guys give us an
overview high-level ovo but also about
what Oslo is and what the components of
Oslo are Don and I have we're in the
same room so we're trading off hand
gestures on that and how who wants to
actually speak so I'll take the first
crack and then Don can you know chime in
with some additional data so Oslo in a
nutshell is our effort to enable folks
to do what we call model driven
development and what that means is if
you look at the the space of the world
today and the way people write
applications the way platforms are
written we're finding increasingly that
folks are moving to what we consider a
far more data-driven approach and what
we mean by that is sort of I'll point
out a very emblematic example if you
look at HTML and cascading style sheets
inside of your web browser what you see
there is that you're writing down data
data that outlines how you not
necessarily how you go about doing a
thing but what you would actually like
displayed on the screen as well as what
Styles you'd like associated with it etc
and then the browser loads that data and
then effectively you know for lack of a
better term interprets that intent and
then displays something to the end-user
and so you don't write a whole bunch of
code I like to say you know
would you rather write a web page
utilizing HTML or print F so that's
largely what we're going about doing
with Oslo is allowing folks to write
down data in interesting ways write down
their intent in interesting ways and
then allow people programmers to get
access to that and then have runtimes
that will do something interesting with
that data so we look at things like HTML
we look at things like cascading style
sheets we look at things on the
Microsoft platform like sam'l with WP
fwf being runtimes that can take that
data and do interesting things on your
behalf and the key thing there for
developers is the fact that they write
much less code and the key thing for
developers also is that they're far more
productive and the key thing for end
users is they get their applications in
a more rapid way and in fact you can get
a broader constituency of people writing
applications if you go with this
particular approach and so Oslo is a
project that's very focused on that we
have three specific pieces
as low one is M which is a language that
allows people to write data down in
addition and it allows people to build
textual dsls that allow them to have
their own interpretation and their own
verbs or their own nouns that pops at
the four-four they're given data we have
a tool called quadrant that allows you
to do the same thing in the visual
domain so you can look at your data then
you can build customized views on top of
that and the last thing that we have is
a set of content a set of models that
you know we ship is a core part of the
platform that then you can extend and
leverage and use and so Oslo is just a
tool chain as well as a tool that allows
you to adopt this model driven approach
of software development and then now
I'll hand it over to Don and he'll fill
in more we're like a jazz band okay you
know if you think about the way the
session holds together we have this
language which is M which is really kind
of the centerpiece of the system we have
quadrant which is this tool that allows
people to interact with them based
information and then we're basically M
enabling a sequel database to be able to
better retain some of the things we're
doing it in after we've compiled down so
nm itself is structured into a three
different sub parts right there is M
grammar M graph and I'm schema can you
can outline what these are all about
yeah it's kind of funny those terms kind
of came out of the PDF you launch the if
you look at the PVC bits which you can
download on our website today
there are fairly bright lines between
the schema design side and the the
textual DSL machinery we're doing a lot
of work in this coming milestone that
we're just entering now to kind of blur
some of those lines because it turns out
there's a lot of things that we were
repeating that is we found ourselves
building the same machinery twice in
subtly different ways for no good reason
and also we just found that there were
scenario reasons where I would want to
be able to write a grammar that was
producing structured data out the rear
end of the parser but I also of course
wanted to schema ties that
and in the current PDC bits we don't
have the machinery in place to pull
those things together
that's kind of the big thrust to this
coming miles I was I don't know that the
term seaman and grammar are gonna live
okay its long term okay but there will
probably still be a way to define data
structures you know like like
metamodeling kind of stuff and then
there is a way to define the concrete
syntax for a textual DSL and the
transformation from that concrete syntax
to the schema you have or the structure
defined before absolutely the
observation is the the lines in the the
bright lines that exist today and the
toolchain will will melt away and you'll
have a common tool chain for being able
to write all of these things down it's
quite often like if you think about it
if you look at the way the the grammar
language works right the grammar
language which is part of em takes
transformations from text into
structured values RAF structured data it
turns out that the scheme it ization
piece of the language schematized this
graph structured data right now in the
current fish ascribe a type to the
output of a language textual DSL we're
in the process of we recently had an
episode about parcel technology where we
had a co Visser on the on the show and
we talked about ll and ll star and ll k
and other you know scandalous parsing
now one thing I saw that was very
interesting when I looked at your at
your PDC presentations was two things
first of all your parcel definition the
grammar language and the tooling was
completely interactive with the
intellibid thing which I really liked
and the other thing is that I probably I
would imagine that you have ways of
combining grammars in a way that does
not run into the usual grammar
ambiguities stuff do you want to maybe
elaborate a little bit on that yeah we
can talk a little bit about that I'm
certainly the interactive grammar of
authoring and debugging mode has just
been transformational in terms of the
way people think about writing a
language I mean it certainly when I went
to school you know Lex and Yak were kind
of the state of depriving and you know
kind of the the the interactive
cycle was left a lot to be desired and I
think the investment we made in getting
a good tooling experience of has paid
off in spades I don't think people would
think about the language the same way if
it didn't have you know this is
inclusive encompassing environment so
that's definitely a huge piece of it and
in terms of language composition there's
some interesting interactions if you
look at the way our language processing
stack is built with a GL our parser on
top of a fairly straightforward lexer
and there's some interaction between the
two where we actually can flip lexical
spaces midstream inside of a Lang okay
that's the destined to the key right
yeah so there there's a feature in our
stack in our runtime stack that enabled
us to flip lectures on the fly it's
exposed through a language construct
that we're not happy we weren't happy
with and we couldn't get it right in
time for PVC so we specifically didn't
make a big deal about that feature yeah
there's a keyword called nest which
turns bold when you type your grammar so
we didn't do we didn't try to hide it we
just didn't try to make a big deal about
it because we don't going to change it
yeah and one of the things we're doing
actually kind of like right now Paul
Vicks working which you Lapera on how to
get a more seamless transition between
different lexical spaces but I think you
know we we have basic functionality
there today
it's usability of it isn't great and so
right now we're doing is focusing a lot
on is there a simpler underlying model
it allows us to deal with things like
token token ambiguity and overlapping
lexical spaces right so I think m3 will
will come up with something better
chemistry by the way is the third
milestone we're about to enter and in
tally pad is that more or less a
prototyping tool and will it merge into
quadrant and and or is it like the kind
of stuff you're gonna keep her on for
Grandma development I think the answer
is probably yes to all of those let me
answer them in order the plan is
absolutely that Intelli pad will be
inside of quadrant
right quadrant is the shelf for Oslo
that's the way where we write really are
investing in building a lot of
interactive environment features that
are very data-driven if you look at
quadrant it boots off the database right
quadrant is like one of the first heavy
abusers of em because they basically
schematize a lot of their runtime load
those that modeling data to boot the
tool so we absolutely believe that
quadrant is the long-term investment for
the shell and we're spending a lot of
time again in this coming milestone of
doing a good job of integrating the
intellipedia experience inside of
quadrant that's dated you know we do
want to keep supporting this kind of
stand-alone experience with Intel apat
with iPad eggsy
I'm simply because it gives you a very
lightweight very purposed focused
experience right purely focused on text
where's quadrant we're really trying to
be inclusive of lots of different UX
styles that is both text but also
diagrammatic a Buehler so so that also
means that within quadrant then you'll
have you know a way of customizing the
editor for for a textual language you
know to customize code completion or to
customize an Okie build coloring or you
know all these kinds of things kind of
the exercise we're going through right
now I'm part of the team is off going
off and looking at what would it look
like to use Intel apat everywhere you
wrote text inside a quadrant right which
means the upside if we can pull that off
and there's some interesting technical
challenges but if we can pull that off
and we're talking down to like the
little property editor level it's a
pretty deep commitment yeah um which
puts a lot of intense pressure on the
text editing engine performance wise
yeah we can pull it off and yes what
that means is I get a grammar first time
it means I get consistent key bindings
across all of my text boxes um so if
I've set up my key bindings to be Emacs
mode I can hit control a everywhere in
the tool and it does what I expect but
also the it does allow me to get you
know basically syntax driven language
services right anywhere inside of the
tool which again we think it's just a
super compelling feature yep so there's
there's a group of people who are
focused full time right now and make
that so how does Oslo fit into the the
Greater Microsoft strategy or something
when you when you published or or
release the DSL tools I don't know two
years ago or something I personally had
the impression that you know kind of
nobody else except the DSL tools team
cared much so so how is this gonna be
with with with Oslo well what's you know
what's the how does it fit into the
overall strategy here Microsoft it's a
very good question i I think what we've
seen we released a DSL toolkit in 2005
and we've actually seen a number of ISPs
and a number of internal customers you
know picking up those tools primarily
the the use of the DSL toolkit is around
what we call visual dsls yep so it gives
you the ability to graphically go in and
create you know various boxes and line
notations for a given domain and we
think that's a fantastic tool chain we
think it actually gives folks a lot of
power to do cogeneration etc and it's in
the space that we sort of when we just
kind of step back and talk about how we
think about modeling in general we sort
of break down modeling into three facets
one is you know just drawings or
diagrams which utilize Visio and other
tools or whiteboard for yeah the other
one is what we would call model driven
development and this is what people
typically you know call modeling which
is where you do things at a certain
conceptual level and then there's lots
of code generation that will actually
you know bind you to a given runtime or
to a given implementation and Oslo isn't
primarily focused on either one of those
two particular things we're very focused
on as I was saying previously what we
call model driven runtimes and model
driven applications and you know we view
things like HTML and the browser things
like sam'l and WPF sam'l and WF is being
sort of the core or center of what we're
trying to do with Oslo but we do want to
have a great story that spans all three
of those different particular spaces so
we're spending a lot of time working
with the DSL a team which is also
responsible for really building the core
infrastructure for our UML support so we
as you know we in
bounced poor UML support that'll be
coming out in deb 10 and we are rien
gauging with OMG and we're participating
very actively in that process and how
we're going about building the UML tools
is actually utilizing the dsl toolkit in
order to enable that so we're spending a
good amount of time key short who is on
our team and had worked on the DSL
toolkit prior is working right now to
get us a good lever point between the
DSL tools and ozlowe and we see that
having a couple different ways but the
primary thing that we want to be able to
enable is that you can have schema ties
data that you can have your your visual
DSL written in the DSL toolkit map down
to and then you can interact at the data
layer at the EM graft level effectively
and then interoperate with the Oslo tool
chain and that's just sort of the tip of
the iceberg that's what we see you know
happening at an initial level in
addition Cameron Skinner who is the pom
and drives the the team architect team
which owns the DSL toolkit as well as
UML tools is committed very deeply to
this notion of supporting the repository
supporting the notion of modeling etc
and we've just got to really sit down
and figure out how we effectively bridge
the gap between the two sort of
technology pillars and make sure our
customers have a great story across both
of those particular products as well as
scenarios so one thing I was wondering
is why you focus in Oslo exclusively on
on interpretation or data driven
applications as opposed to cogeneration
because I mean obviously both of them
have there have their benefits for
example I mean if you look at the
embedded space there isn't much
interpret that stuff going on for the
abyss performance reasons so why did you
or why do you focus specifically on the
on the data driven or the interpreted
side well I'll give my perspective and
then you know Don mate may differ on
that from my standpoint we've sort of
viewed this as us coming from our
natural center of gravity so many of us
that are on the team had been very
focused on how do we write down schema
size message-passing that's sort of
where many of us on the team sort of
started now we've we've added additional
people under the team
in the way we went about doing that is
we built this thing called indigo or the
windows communication foundation and it
ended up becoming a very data-driven
framework where what we effectively did
was we could go look at the wisdom and
then build a runtime stack that would be
driven completely off that wisdom and
the way the messages would interact with
each other as well as the message
descriptions and we found that to be an
incredibly powerful and flexible
approach to how we developed WCS itself
as well as how we sort of focus that to
an end-user developer and then the next
step for us really was we started
working on windows workflow and many of
us that had worked on that and we sort
of merged the efforts and we saw that
that was really taking it to the next
level which is where you weren't just
doing message passing but you were
literally going down and doing things at
a very very almost imperative level but
doing it in a very data-driven way that
you could change and mutate and it would
be very flexible and very transparent
and that was really the center of
gravity for us and then when we looked
across the entire Microsoft platform we
saw that this was happening again and
again and again go look at its WPF is a
great example you go look at asp.net
asp.net does utilize code generation but
a lot of the data binding a lot of the
the underlying things that go on inside
of the framework or driven off steal are
metadata and so what we saw was if you
could really get things into a
transparent description there was a lot
of power to be gained there and so you
know I think cogeneration is fantastic I
think it absolutely has an approach but
you know what we're trying to solve with
ozlowe is that everyone who was building
one of these what I would call a you
know a data-driven runtime was writing
their own tools right they were writing
effectively their own you know set of
languages oftentimes XML based they were
writing their own infrastructure and so
what ozlowe really is for us is us
looking across the platform and saying
hey let's build a consistent tool that
enables these sorts of runtimes let's
build a consistent language that allows
people to schema ties that data as well
as add their own experiences on top of
that let's go build some core models
much like we did with that in that
framework around the base class
libraries to enable this kind of
development so at the end of the day I
view Oslo is just a step on our
path from the dinette framework where
we're just entering the next level of
software development so Donald yeah look
I I agree with everything Doug said okay
couple couple more things one is solving
the the runtime problem is strictly
harder there there's a different set of
challenges but I think that there are a
set of challenges that if we put off too
long will constantly be in this kind of
it's a static world that can't react
dynamic hungry now so so we're trying to
optimize for the more dynamic
environment knowing that yes we will
have to do more work to make some static
optimizations happen but you know did I
mean the Intel apat experience is a
great example right we optimized for
dynamic environments so that we could
get a highly interactive no you touch it
you change it you know it's it's a much
more fluid environment and we kind of
want it we want to enable that
everywhere we go but that stated if you
look at Oslo core we don't tell people
how to use the data they write down in
EM if they want to do coach Taylor again
I can tell you right now I know there
are people out in the world doing T for
templates against the output of the
parser in fact the great irony is we do
cogeneration ok no and the reason why I
was asking is that I'm involved in a
couple of large fish model driven
projects in in the embedded space and
what what already works quite well is
cogeneration what doesn't really work
that well is managing large and/or many
models and that's where I guess you're
your repository comes in so if I would
imagine I have the Oslo to a technology
available you know really good grandma
support really good nice front end with
quadrant and a really good scalable
database repository kind of thing and
then a good cogeneration engine for my
embedded customers that would be really
really interesting so was wondering why
I mean I understand now that that's the
starting point the the interpreted world
and that at some point a more generative
approach might be added in some fashion
well what I'd say hey it sounds like you
got a great idea you want to come build
it - I think that is the natural
conclusion you have to reach when you
look at what we were calling
you know model model focused and model
driven development if you really think
about is Don said if you can reflect
over the models and then run something
like our t4 across that I see no reason
why you can't bring these four
approaches together at all sure I mean
my impression is also that the code
generation stuff is there are a couple
of good tools out there I mean they
might have to be ported but otherwise
they're available the bigger challenge
is really the editor and the repository
so it's obviously really good that you
address this first yeah is the other day
we believe that structured data is the
way you should drive things and if you
want to drive cogeneration off that love
it
sure absolutely so talking about this
this repository thing again I well
I contradict myself now I just said yeah
of course I mean I don't know I would
let's say it differently differently why
don't you make this an option for the
user to either use the big database or
files and you know what we absolutely
have that so if you look at the way you
develop content for our platform it's
all file based right you go into an
telepods you write a model down you save
a file you write a grammar definition
you save a grammar definition so all
that is file based because we know
developers are they've got tons of tools
that are very humiliated with text yeah
you know I don't know how to differ
database the only way I know the
diffident is to get it into files and
different although I'm sure there are
many tools and I'll get lots of email as
a result of that statement with lots of
proposals but at the end of the day we
think there's there's room for both and
we think many developers will stay in
the file world that said when you want
to have a tool and you want to do
analysis like we want to enable on top
of quadrant you really need a query
processor I mean that's really at the
end of the day what it boils down to is
how can I do queries across potentially
massive data sets in a performant way
yeah and at the end of the day it turns
out that's one of the reasons we're
betting on the relational model and it
turns out that's one of the reasons that
we embrace sequel is a core runtime for
us
as it has this performer query processor
yeah so so actually there is a very
interesting discussion going on about
some of my colleagues and friends about
what the correct or better metaphor for
this model world is is it the database
you know with a query processor and and
all that what you just talked about or
is it more like the IDE we typically use
Eclipse as an example where the data is
actually in files but then the the ide
builds all those indices and registries
and stuff for efficient whirring so and
i'm i'm well we didn't really decide yet
which of those two approaches is the is
the you know is the one that should be
influencing the model driven world more
I believe it's both I think you're going
to see us like let's take for example
source control there's most most source
control things in the world of very file
based so we believe people will write
their content and check it in and out of
models we also think what people will do
is load their models into the repository
didn't get exactly what you just said
which is I get this IDE this tool like
experience and then we think people may
make a decision that they actually want
to export and then check back in you
know the result of that work and so I
think you actually want to have a center
of gravity that embraces both approaches
hmm
in in some of the videos I saw from PDC
you you talked quite a bit about the
analogy of Oslo to exit to the XML world
do you want to maybe elaborate on that
briefly John do you want elaborate on
that one I'm on record as saying lots of
things I'd love to get you on record
talking about oh sure look yeah this
makes sure that I can point back to the
podcast next week and say look what you
said yeah well look a lot of the things
people do with XML are pretty
interesting I've definitely been you
know one of the big abusers of XML maybe
my colleagues on this team in fact I
tell Don I make a joke I say we're doing
penance for what were you done hopefully
we'll get atonement yeah but no look I
you know there's a lot of parallel in
terms of
the problem space right there's an
abstract data model ours is based on
label label directed graphs the info
said is based on kind of a
generalization of the w3c Dom there's a
at least one concrete textual syntax yep
I mean there's a lot we have schema I
mean there's a lot of pieces that are
similar in terms of life the kind of
thing they do of course they're build
very differently they're designed around
a fine points but certainly a lot of the
things you can do with XML we think
about doing with with Oslo and I think
that's all well good I thought Doug was
gonna go I'm gonna try and out Doug
Purdy here for a second
quadrant is our info path right you know
if you think about woody InfoPath did
which I love great I love that yeah good
I really love InfoPath fact what yeah I
really love him go pass an info pass for
me was kind of like this really great
let's just live the dream let's go all
the way with XML and it had some success
in the marketplace which is great but
you know quadrant is very much in that
that ilk right we're we're basically
trying to bootstrap an entire tool chain
on top of this basic little data model
in syntax so yes there are lots of
parallels and I think a lot of the
things people do today with XML they're
gonna do with so another analogy I think
done actually you mentioned it in one of
the PDC talks is a comparison with the
small talk and I found that rather
interesting yes it's interesting
everyone on my team breaks down into a
small talker or a lisper and so all
anybody's trying to do is actually
develop one of those two environments
yes it does this small talk yeah
actually I think everyone's broken down
the small talk I think there's one small
talker
and yeah I'm Melissa Pettit yeah I mean
certainly you know we're trying to there
were some great ideas there and there's
lots of lots of great ideas that have
can still be fodder for works of
commercial software it's great
I have no problem you know paying homage
to the great Joe yeah it's great it's
great you know the more good ideas we
can get from small talk and Lisbon yeah
I mean bring forward I think is great
certainly the the whole interpreted
dynamic approach and also the ability to
reflect over everything and change
everything with its own means and have
this quadrant thing describing itself
and stuff that's very very small talk
like yeah the other day I for me there's
a design point which is to abolish
distinction between runtime and design
time front i i don't think that serves
either developers or end-users at all
they have their bright line yep so going
back to the to the to the core features
i have two more questions there one is
will it be possible to mix graphical and
textual languages so what I'm thinking
about is imagine you have a state
machine that's modeled graphically and
then within the state machine you have
some kind of expression language you can
use for the guard conditions although
the actions in the States or something
like that and then of course this
textual language has the whole you know
the whole stuff code completion syntax
highlighting and all you want in place
yeah we do that today I mean if you look
at the way I write visual data cells in
quadrants today they are largely
structured data but they often have
expression trees at the leave yeah
also if you look at the dumb F the FF v
v2 or whatever we're calling the one the
ships and dotnet for the one that we're
working on right now that's another
great example where we use structured
data kind of abuses animal data
structure for a lot of stuff but then we
kind of bottomed out at embedded link
expressions which get turned into um so
I think there's a lot of lot of lot of
Merit to that approach I think the next
iteration of the catalog in Oslo will
look a lot like that as well in the the
the interesting thing is in a world
where you've got parsing and compilation
machinery as part of the runtime
platform it so the line doesn't have to
be as bright we can make decisions like
I'm going to store this sub part of my
program as tax knowing I can easily
reconstitute it because I've kept enough
information from previous compilations
to be able to reconstruct what I need it
shouldn't
I think I think there's a lot of we have
a lot of flexibility in some knobs to
turn you you mentioned link do you use
link prominently in in Oslo I don't
think we have any implementations of
iqueryable that's - hey look we you know
we're C sharp does we are I should are
building this in c-sharp I know we use
many c-sharp trio features yeah I don't
think we're heavy link abusers what I
was thinking about was how you would
write views and our queries or stuff you
know whether that expression language is
basically the the same expression
language as the one used and linked or
whether it's different
so the expression language that we use
got now I understand
so the expression language we use in M
is you know we use curly brace syntax we
use certain c-sharp syntactic idioms and
yeah we use query comprehensions that
look a lot like c-sharp okay we also use
a link query syntax in the tool for
building customization of visual so yes
in that respect yes the LINQ query
comprehension detection so one thing
that that that certainly plays a role in
modern development in in my world and I
suppose it is also important in your
world is transforming one model one set
of abstractions into another set of
abstractions or you know the whole topic
about model to model transformations do
you have any specific thoughts and tools
and and and whatever about that go back
to the XML question which I think is
there's a related point here yeah
exercise wanted to have it in an
integrated language where we could write
down values constraints over values and
query function transformation over
values and you know we we wanted to have
a single way to do all those things and
kind of an integrated way to do all
those things and you know we do come up
with these names like M graph and M
grammar and all these things so that we
can kind of help people think about
slices of the language but we definitely
think we need all those things and we're
trying to come up with again as simple a
possible approach that'll work to get
all that thing those things but yeah
right now you know people write computed
values in them which give you a
different
shape over the an existing schema we
think that's super important the thing
we talked about doing and I don't know
how close we'll get in v1 we've talked
about having the general purpose pattern
matching system yeah all right great now
the the we have pattern matching
overtaxed yeah because it's kind of hard
to build it a parser without it sure
nobody want is this pattern matching
over structured data metadata driven
that's a really useful yeah and how far
will get interview one I don't know but
we certainly you know our our appetites
are unbounded so we kind of wouldn't get
there eventually we have to ship stuff
along the way yeah this is all a notion
of pragmatics we've had many incubations
going on in this group that have been
very focused on that particular problem
and we've got a lot of great ideas in
the space but yet again it comes down to
we've got a ship mm-hmm sure another
thing of course now that you're you know
increasing your your involvement with
the OMG you could actually adopt the you
know qvt standard for models model
transformations something you thought
about no I haven't in well you know we
have a lot of thoughts around the UML
standard but that's primarily where we
spend a lot of our time thinking about
the OMG assets you know but I'm always
willing to you know consider other
alternatives to how we might solve our
customers problems so right now that's
not some we're looking at actually not
quite sure that qvt is actually that
useful that that's what I was laughing a
little bit okay so two more questions
on my sheet here one is how open Oslo is
gonna be do you have any plans about
cooperating integrating with other let's
say model driven environments like let's
say eclipse for example I know that you
talked with Admirals about some of that
yeah great question so we don't think
that we can be successful getting this
approach in the industry or meeting
Microsoft goals unless we have a very
broad base of adoption throughout the
industry we just don't think it's
possible and so as part of that when we
went to PDC
an ounce PM language etc we made it a
very conscious decision and I think a
very important decision that we were
going to release the language
specification under the OSP and what
that means the open specification
promised it effectively means that
anyone can implement the language and we
won't you know we effectively promised
that you can implement that language and
we won't do anything about it in fact we
encourage you to do that
and this is one of the mechanisms that
we use for things like the WS star
standards etc and I think that's just an
initial foray into the space I think
you'll be hearing a lot more from us as
you said I've been having some good
conversations with Ed we've been talking
with some folks in Apache what I really
want to see happen is I want to see em
and this approach of data-driven
development in this approach of you know
writing down values in a nice compact
way writing down transformations in a
nice compact way writing down ski
immunization of that those values then
in a very compact straightforward human
friendly way I'd like to see that on as
many platforms as humanly possible so I
think you'll see us doing lots of things
to encourage that again and again and
again and we really want to make this
approach be something central to the way
people write software across all
platforms now that said you know a lot
of platforms have already adopted this
notion of being model driven model
assisted development and we would like
to embrace that as well I mean we have
the same thing in our platform with like
the DSL toolchain so how do we integrate
with it you know we have Eclipse and
there's a great set of standards around
eclipse how do we integrate with that so
you know these are all conversations I'm
open to having and I want to have em as
an implementation on as many platforms
as we can possibly get and then find the
right level of integration points that
we need to make our customers successful
and make the industry successful moving
to this particular approach I mean if I
had my druthers M would be as ubiquitous
as XML okay well it really would be in
as many platforms and is and is
integrated deeply into both tooling as
well as the way that people think about
their space yeah because if you go look
at XML today it largely is the mecca
by which people write more textual dsls
than anything else if you want to call
the textual details
yeah yeah well I mean it you know in
fact people yeah it's you know what is
it textual DSL but yeah at the end of
the day it's what people utilize so they
don't have to go write their own parser
but in bed their own notion of
domain-specific constructs for their
runtimes yeah and you see that again you
see that in the Java platform you see
that the dotnet platform I you know
every Enterprise application I see these
days has some you know on the side you
know data-driven saying that's primary
active L base absolutely camp and and
and and I mean XML is a good way of
storing structured data it's just not a
good way of you know to interact with
the data from the human perspective
because there is no custom syntax that's
exactly right and so what we what we're
trying to do with özil if you look at
some of the design points you know we
talked about the database you know we're
developing a value model and a schema
today ssin model as well as a
transformation model that's very
database friendly and the reason we're
doing that is we need that query
processor etc but at the same time we're
developing this ability to be very human
friendly in the interaction syntax and
the way that you you interact with that
structured data and the set of values
and so and we view Oslo and M in
particular as being the mechanism to
bridge the human friendly back to the
database or to you know any storage that
you have and so that's a key value for
us and we think that that's one of the
things that's gonna really make this
approach stand out yeah I mean I I I'm
really a big believer in this the whole
model driven data driven stuff because
it allows you if you do it right to
really solve the legacy problem because
now you don't you know implement stuff
in unreadable and an unprocessed and
transformable code but rather in in
models which are separated by a
viewpoint and and then of course this
whole approach only makes sense if the
stuff is open because if you don't have
a way of transforming your now I don't
know Oslo or Eclipse or oMG models into
the next new standard once it becomes
available then it's kind of pointless so
that's why I think this really needs to
be open yep no I absolutely agree and
we're gonna do everything that we can to
to make the the
the EM specification is open as we can
possibly make it and you know at the OSP
is just you know in my view when we're
having lots of conversations just the
the initial sort of foray into this and
I think you'll see a lot more from us in
the in the near future
yeah so since you already mentioned the
word future what about the current state
what's the release plan what's the
availability when is there going to be a
1.0 lease you know what's the strategy
what's the plan
good questions looking right at me
that's a great question so right now
there are bits that are available we
release those at PDC and it's actually
what I call pre-alpha and what I mean by
that is actually let me step back a
little bit what we're trying to do
something a little different with what
we're doing with Oslo we're trying to
engage as early and as often and as
openly as we can with this particular
approach and this particular release and
what that means is you're gonna see us
dropping a lot more frequently than most
teams inside of Microsoft do that you'll
also see us re reacting far more to
community input and wanting to get the
community very involved in what we're
developing and I think in addition to
that this is going to be we'll see how
it plays out but one of the ideas we
have is that we really want to engage
the community in helping us determine
when it's done and you know when it's
viable when it's something that people
can can build on and that's relatively
new at least for some of us that there
are other parts of Microsoft that have
already adopted that approach that's
that's fairly new for when we think
about platform technologies at Microsoft
yeah so you know to answer your question
when do we think ab1 will be I don't
really know I kind of have a good idea
in my mind about what we need to deliver
in that space but we're relying on a lot
of customer feedback to help us get a
good understanding of what we need to
deliver as well as community feedback
especially if we aspire to be
an XML like technology this open is
widely adopted and ubiquitous is that
there's a lot of people that we need to
get input from many of which I hopefully
are listening to podcasts many of folks
that actually worked on XML etc and we
want to start those conversations and I
think you know will
work in concert with the community and
then we can make a determination on when
we're done but I think what you'll see
us doing is we'll be doing another drop
soon hopefully that will be in the early
winter I think you'll see us also want
to do additional sets of drops around
events
our plans are there's a mixed conference
that's coming up you'll likely see us
doing something around that there's Tech
Ed you'll likely see doing something
around that yeah I think that Lane
Gannett is coming up you'll likely see
us doing something around that so I mean
we'll see but like these v1 technologies
I've worked on a couple of them it's
very hard to be able to make an accurate
prediction on when you're done for v2
and v3 it's much easier because a lot of
times you can be de triv and you can be
revenue driven these things but the
answer question I just don't know we're
gonna make it as fast as we can
well but I mean actually this is a good
answer because it says that you're only
gonna ship once it has reached a state
of maturity and also feature completely
makes sense we have a new person on the
call we're actually now joining we're
just finishing up a podcast and I guess
Carol used the same exact conference
number no it's fine it's fine to stay on
the call hey Marcus the whole entire
Oslo leadership is dialing into this
call okay so now joining actually I mean
we're almost finished the only thing I
was gonna ask is what did I forget to
ask what do you want to say when you
know anybody of the other people who
just joined what do you want to say to
our listeners when we shut down this
cast
no I appreciate it and Marcus I
appreciate you offering up the
opportunity for us to come and talk a
little bit about Oslo sure and I would
encourage anyone who's listening to go
check out the bits if nothing else you
should install windows just to run Oslo
you can go to msdn.microsoft.com slash
Oslo and our SDK is available there
I'd love to get feedback and my email
address is Douglas P at microsoft.com
and if you send me mail I promise
somebody will get back to you okay thank
you very much and well good luck with
with with the development of Oslo I'll
certainly stay in touch yes thank you so
much Marcus but I've enjoyed reading
your blog you've had some good feedback
that you've already pumped sort of into
the engineering theme so thank you no
thanks bye all right all right thank you
thanks Marcus
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website at st - radio
dot length if you want to support us you
can donate to the SE radio team via the
website or you can advertise for su
radio for example by clicking on the
dick reddit delicious and slash dog
puppies to contact the team please send
email to team @ SE - radio net or if it
is specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under a
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pod safe music
network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle
[Music]
you